A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, Counsel's Office, Series 10 FA358
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, Counsel's Office, Series 10
1958-1966
Rockefeller Archive Center
Whiteman, Michael
Douglass, Robert R.
Corbin, Sol Neil
Boyd, Joseph H.
Cannon, James M.
New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
Morrow, Hugh
Whitman, Ann
New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service
Ronan, William J. (William John)
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights
FA358
69.96 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as governor of New York from January 1, 1959, to December 18, 1973. He was the first person elected to four consecutive four-year terms as a state governor.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 15 10
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Appointments Office (FA353)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Assembly and Senate Memos (FA354)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Joseph H. Boyd (FA355)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, James Cannon (FA356)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Affirmative Action (N. Lee Cook) (FA357)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York State Committee to Reelect the President (FA359)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Jerry A. Danzig (FA360)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Executive Chamber (FA361)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, 55th Street (FA362)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Issue Books (FA363)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Arthur Massolo (FA364)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Hugh Morrow (FA242)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Office (FA365)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Civil Service Resolutions (Charles H. Palmer) (FA366)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Political Files (FA367)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Press Office (FA368)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Public Relations (FA369)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Departmental Reports (FA370)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, William J. Ronan (FA371)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Speeches (FA372)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Diane Van Wie (FA373)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial (FA374)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Gene Wyckoff (FA375)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Republican State Fund Raising Reports (FA376)
Arrangement note
This series is divided into four subseries:
Subseries 1 - Robert MacCrate Subseries 2 - Sol Neil Corbin Subseries 3 - Robert R. Douglass Subseries 4 - Michael Whiteman
Scope and Contents note
The primary responsibility of Counsel to the Governor was to translate the Governor's programs into law. He and his staff ensured that bills were correctly drafted, and helped to stop bills that were antithetical to the Governor's programs from being enacted. Bills in the governor's annual legislative program were drafted in the counsel's office to ensure that they reflected Rockefeller's views. Drafting work was divided among assistant counsels, roughly according to subject matter. The counsel's office also reviewed bills drafted by other agencies. Rockefeller was not directly involved in this work, concentrating instead on broad policy matters. Under Rockefeller's administrations the Counsel was one of three people, along with the Secretary to the Governor and the Budget Director, on whom he relied most heavily for administration and program development.
From Robert H. Connery and Gerald Benjamin, "Rockefeller of New York: Executive Power in the Statehouse," (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1979), pp. 121-122.
Vice-Presidents -- United States; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Human rights; Arms control; Affirmative action programs -- New York (State); International relations -- United States; Latin America; International economic relations; International relations; New York (State); Political campaigns -- United States; Legislation -- New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Political science; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Public policy; Public relations; State governments -- United States; United States; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Civil service -- New York (State); Economics; Federal government -- United States; Government policy; Arms control -- United States; Civil defense; Civil defense -- United States; Civil service; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- )
- Robert MacCrate, Bulk, 1959-1962 1958-1966, bulk 1959-1962; bulk; 1; 4 Document Box(es)
  Scope and Contents note
  NOTE TO RESEARCHERS
  This subseries contains a portion of the office files of Robert MacCrate and other members of the office of Counsel to the Governor. They document the official activities of these individuals in the execution of their duties as members of Nelson A. Rockefeller's gubernatorial staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administrations and political campaigns. However, unless a document is personally signed by Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document personally signed by him, it should not be assumed that he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
  SCOPE AND CONTENT
  This subseries contains a small portion of the files of Robert MacCrate, who served as Associate Counsel (Feb. 2, 1959-June 1, 1959) and then Counsel (June 1, 1959-June 30, 1962) to Governor Rockefeller. The principal topics are constitutional amendments (Folder 10), coordination of state governmental activities and departments (Folder 11-14), economic development (Folder 25), and education (Folder 26-35). Other files deal with the creation of the Job Development Authority (Folder 25), state aid to public schools (Folders 29-31), the merger of the University of Buffalo into the State University of New York (Folder 32), and the creation of the State Dormitory Authority (Folders 33 and 35).
  These files also include memos from MacCrate's predecessor, Roswell B. "Rod" Perkins, who served as Counsel to Governor Rockefeller for his first six months in office, and memos from MacCrate's successor, S. Neil Corbin, who served as Assistant Counsel (Jan. 14, 1959-June 1, 1961) and then Counsel (July 1, 1962-Sept. 1, 1965) to Governor Rockefeller.
  - Budget - State Aid Studies, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Historical studies of state aid by Department of Budget; confidential report by Robert MacCrate to T. Norman Hurd with counsel comments; Budget's state aid recommendations; potential state aid program proposals for 1962-1963; summaries of state aid reports, broken down by program area.
  - Carlino, Speaker Joseph F., & Staff, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence from R. J. Edsell (cousel to Speaker) to Robert MacCrate re status reports on pending bills; Speaker's staff assignments.
  - Chiropractors, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondence re chiropractor licensing.
  - Citizen's Committee for Children of New York, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Correspondence re Citizen's Committee; remarks on proposed new Family Court Act.
  - Citizen's Union, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Reports, notes and correspondence re Citizen's Union legislative proposals; handwritten notes (author unkown).
  - Civil Defense, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Memo re "Fall-out Shelters," 1961; memo re civil defense, 1962.
  - Civil Service - Employee Relations, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Report "Relations Between New York State and its Employees."
  - Commerce Department, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Memoranda and correspondence re business climate; New York State magazine ads re business development; legislation program proposals; Job Development Authority bill, 1961, and implementation of Job Development Authority; Commerce Department meeting, 1961; Commerce Department Program Legislation.
  - Comptroller - Audit Reports, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Memos re closure of audit reports (no audit reports in file).
  - Constitutional Amendments, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Memos re Constitutional Amendments; Job Development Authority, Gubernatorial Succession, Suffrage (length of New York State residence); minutes of Temporary State Commission on the Revision and Simplification of the Constitution.
  - Coordination Commission, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Robert MacCrate appointment to Temporary State Commission on Coordination of State Activities; minutes of Commission meetings; progress reports.
  - Coordination Commission, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    1960 Tentative Report and Report of Commission; correpondence.
  - Coordination Commission, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    1961 Report of Commission; correpondence.
  - Coordination Planning Board, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Press release, 6/1/61; NAR "establishes an Office for Regional Development and a Planning Coordination Board within the Executive Department;" correspondence; memos re historical review of planning; planning conference schedules.
  - Corporation Law Revision, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Legislative Document (1958) No. 23, Second Interim Report of Joint Legislative Committee to Study Revision of Corporation Law; Legislative Document (1959) No. 39, Third Interim Report; Senate Int. 3124, Pr. 3316 (1960), new Business Corporation Law; correspondence; Robert MacCrate memo, 3/24/60, to NAR recommending cooperation with Joint Legislative Committee returned by NAR with handwritten note, "Bo - Just what we want. Excellent! Nelson".
  - Correction Department, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Letter to Sol Neil Corbin from Correction Commissioner McGinnis re transfer of the Division of Parole from Correction Department to New York State Judicial Conference; response by Sol Neil Corbin: "We will keep you advised."
  - Correction Guards' Salaries, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Two memos, T. Norman Hurd to NAR re proposed salary increase.
  - Correction Department - Prison Work, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Memos re: construction work on prison camps by inmates, union waiver; questionable incarceration of material witness at Onondaga County Jail.
  - Council of Churches, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Two legislative releases.
  - Counsel's Office; Bill Jacket Memo Acknowledgments, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Form letter thanking addressees for assistance and input re legislation, and responses.
  - Counsel's Office; Bill Jacket Requests, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Memos re 1956 harness track legislation and request for copy of bill jacket from "Sam Roseman's law firm." On original memo from Roswell B. "Rod" Perkins to NAR, NAR writes "OK" twice, and "Good I like it" regarding Roswell B. "Rod" Perkins's recommendation. Requests for examination of bill jackets, denials on grounds of policy. Correspondence with Governor Harriman and staff re: Harriman policy re release of bill jacket contents, copy of Harriman letter, 5/30/63, authorizing release of bill jackets fro 1955-1958.
  - Criminal Identification and Intelligence System, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Proposal by System Development Corporation, 4/8/64.
  - Data Processing, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Memos re establishment of state government data processing.
  - East Hudson Parkway Authority, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    NAR press release and memo re transfer of Westchester County Parkways to East Hudson Parkway Authority.
  - Economic Development and Expansion, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Reports, press releases and proposals re economic expansion; Job Development Authority (originally called Industrial Development Authority); draft by-laws for state advisory councils; memo summarizing final report of Temporary State Commission on Economic Expansion.
  - Education - General, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Memos, news clippings, status reports, correspondence, press releases re school financing; confidential State University of New York report, "Trends in Public School Expenditures and the Factors Affecting Immediate and Long Range Educational Costs," October 1959; legislative program proposals.
  - Education - General, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Legislative proposals, correspondence, reports, Regents' Legislative Proposals for 1962; confidential State University of New York report, "Education for the Sixties - How Much Will It Cost?;" New York City Board of Education Interim Report to Regents; correspondence re Brooklyn Friends School.
  - Education - Extending Public School to 14 Years, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Memo from Frank Wille to Sol Neil Corbin, 9/19/62.
  - Education - Financing - General, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Press release, 1/17/60, Republican State Chairman Morhouse re "School Financing Crisis;" Comptroller's School Financing proposal; Diefendorf Joint Legislative Committee on School Financing, 1961; memos re school aid distribution formulae; New York City school strike; NAR press releases re New York City school funding crisis.
  - Education - Financing - Telephone Excise Tax, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Memos, correspondence, press releases re federal 10% excise tax scheduled to expire 6/30/60; possible state imposition of same tax.
  - Education - Higher - General, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Minutes of State University Program Meetings; correspondence re student loan guarantees; Higher Education Assistance Corporation; legislative proposals by New York State Congress of Parents and Teachers, Inc.; proposal re technical education; 1962 tuition increases; state aid to City University of New York; correspondence with State University of New York President Thomas H. Hamilton.
  - Education - Higher - State University - Buffalo Merger, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Merger of University of Buffalo with State University of New York; summary statement re merger proposal by John R. Davison, Esq., January 1961; correspondence, news clippings, memos, financial data; draft merger agreement, February 1962; memo to NAR from Roswell B. "Rod" Perkins, 5/18/62, re "Historical Analysis" of merger.
  - Education - Higher - State University Construction Fund, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Memos re proposed "State University of New York Building Authority"; correspondence, memos re legislation; press releases; memo Robert MacCrate to NAR, 3/19/62, with NAR handwritten comments and direction "Take up with Bob & Bill re possible call to Chancellor & Regents."
  - Education - Higher - State University, Criminology, School of, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Memo re proposed School of Criminology in State University.
  - Education - Higher - Dormitory Authority, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Memos, press releases and correspondence re proposed Dormitory Authority.
- Sol Neil Corbin, 1958-1965; 2; 5 Document Box(es)
  This subseries contains the office files of Sol Neil Corbin and other members of the office of Counsel to the Governor. They document the official activities of these individuals in the execution of their duties as members of Nelson A. Rockefeller's gubernatorial staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administrations and political campaigns. However, unless a document is personally signed by Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document personally signed by him, it should not be assumed that he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
  This subseries contains a small portion of the files of Sol Neil Corbin, who served as Assistant Counsel (Jan. 14, 1959-June 1, 1961) and then Counsel (July 1, 1962-Sept. 1, 1965) to Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller. The principal topics are housing and urban renewal. Major issues include the creation of the New York State Housing Finance Agency (folders 7-8), and the consolidation, clarification and simplification of urban renewal and housing laws (folders 19-20). Some of the files include clippings on related issues such as abuses and possible corruption in urban renewal projects financed by the federal government (folder 15), and a 1960 proposition for $15 million in subsidies for low-rent housing (folder 12). There is also a file of outgoing correspondence from the Counsel's office, dated January 1960 to December 1965, covering all manner of topics and authored by various members of the Counsel's Office (folders 22-47).
  - Bill Jackets Policy, 1962, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Samples of letters explaining that bill jackets are not made publicly available during the term of an incumbent governor.
  - Correspondence Form Book for Counsel's Office, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Templates for routine correspondence.
  - Housing - Campaign, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Rod Perkins memo re publicity of NAR's stand on housing issues, analysis of Governor Harriman's record on housing, reports on current housing issues in New York City (relatively little documentation here on NAR's stand on housing and urban renewal issues).
  - Housing - Constitution (New York State), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Robert Prince's draft ammendment to New York State Constitution enabling the state to loan money for housing projects.
  - Housing - Division of Housing (New York State), 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    3 pieces of correspondence and 2 press releases on the legality of certain pieces of urban renewal legislation.
  - Housing - Fiduciary Investments in Housing, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    New York State Departments of Banking, Insurance, and Housing support of bill permitting investments by trust funds in first mortgage bonds of limited profit housing companies.
  - Housing - Finance Agency, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Documentation of the creation and justification of the New York State Housing Finance Agency; proposed legislation, James Gaynor's survey of New York financial professionals on the need for such an agency, John Mitchell memos on issuing bonds by the Housing Finance Agency, gaining tax exempt status for Housing Finance Agency bonds, state insurance of mortgage loans.
  - Housing - Finance Agency, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Housing - "Housing in New York State,", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Background paper by Lee Goodwill sent to Rod Perkins possibly for NAR's 1958 campaign.
  - Housing - Inventory, 1956, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    United States Bureau of the Census reports on national housing inventory, 1956.
  - Housing - Limited Profit Housing Mortgage Corporation, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    3 pieces of correspondence on Limited Profit Housing Mortgage Corporation investment limitations.
  - Housing - Low-Rent, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Clippings and pamphlets for and against Proposition No. 2 (1960) for $5 million state subsidy for low rent housing and urban renewal programs.
  - Housing - Middle Income Housing, Publications, circa 1954-1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Printed and mimeographed information on middle income housing projects, some covering correspondence, 1959-1961.
  - Housing - Slum Eradication, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Drafts of "Certificate of Allocation" and "Certificate of Intent" for the (New York State) Government Emergency Fund.
  - Housing - Title I, Newspaper Clippings, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Articles from New York City newspapers regarding abuses and possible corruption in New York urban renewal projects financed under Title I of the Federal Housing Act of 1949.
  - Press Releases Relating to Counsel's Office, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    An incomplete set of 24 press releases, dated July 18, 1962, to December 7, 1964, announcing programs or policies resulting from work done by the Counsel's Office and annoucing the appointments of new members of the Counsel's staff.
  - Urban Renewal - General, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Proposed laws and ammendments for state financing of housing and urban renewal projects, "An Evaluation of Financing State Aid for Urban Renewal by Capital Grants Rather Than Loans and Periodic Subsidies," December 30, 1960.
  - Urban Renewal - General, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Urban Renewal - Recodification, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Consolidating, clarifying, and simplifying urban renewal and housing laws.
  - Urban Renewal - Recodification, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Urban Renewal - Tenant Relocation, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Memos and schedules on tenant relocation payments.
  - Chronological File
    Copies of outgoing correspondence from the Counsel's Office. These letters and internal memos cover all manner of topics and were authored by different members of the Counsel's Office. The correspondence is dated from January 1960 to December 1965.
    - November-December 1965 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - August-October 1965 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - April-July 1965 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - January-March 1965 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - November-December 1964 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - September-October 1964 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - July-August 1964 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - June 1964 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - March-May 1964 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - January-February 1964 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - November-December 1963 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - September-October 1963 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - July-August 1963 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - April-June 1963 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - January-March 1963 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - December 1962 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - October-November 1962 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - July-September 1962 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - April-June 1962 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - January-March 1962 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - November-December 1961 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - September-October 1961 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - January-August 1961 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - September-December 1960 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - July-August 1969, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - January-June 1960 (Box 5, Folder 47)
- Robert R. Douglass, 1959-1972; 3; 65 Document Box(es)
  Arrangement note
  The files in this subseries are arranged alphabetically by subject matter and then arbitrarily within each subject.
  Biographical/Historical note